Finding Aid for Philip Jay papers, 1925-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip Jay papers 1925-1970
Jay, Philip, 1898-
5 linear feet
851547 Aa 2
Professor of dentistry at the University of Michigan and an early proponent of the use of fluoridation of water as a preventative of tooth decay. Professional papers largely correspondence concerning his teaching and research, the administration of the dental school, and advocacy of fluoridation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Philip Jay (donor no. 4096 ) in 1963. The second accession was received from the U-M Dental Library (donor no. 794 ) in July 2008.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born June 5, 1898 in Detroit, Philip Jay graduated from Detroit Central High School in 1918. After attending Detroit Junior College for one year (1918-19), he enrolled in the U-M School of Dentistry, receiving his D.D.S. degree in 1923. He then attended the U-M School of Graduate Studies, earning his Master of Science degree in 1924.
From 1925 to 1929, Jay served as an associate in bacteriology at the University of Rochester, School of Medicine and Dentistry. In 1929, he came to the University of Michigan School of Dentistry as a research associate, a post he held until 1938 when named research assistant professor. In 1940, Jay was appointed assistant professor of dentistry, associate professor in 1943 and full professor in 1948.
Beginning in 1937 he also served as consultant for the National Institute of Health, U.S. Public Health Service, Washington, D.C. During World War II, he was a consultant for the U.S. Public Health Service at Army Air Force Base, Randolph Field.
Jay researched the bacteriology of, dietary control of, and relationship of fluoride to dental caries. Due to his research into dental caries, he was awarded the Pierre Fauchard Academy's Gold Medal in 1957. [1] During the 1950s and 1960s, he actively campaigned for the fluoridation of Michigan's water supply. During the public debate surrounding fluoridation, Jay testified before the Michigan Legislature, during fluoridation trials, and publicly commented in the media. For his public service, he was awarded the Michigan Public Health Association's first Distinguished Service Award on April 30, 1964.[2]
Jay passed away on December 22, 1974.
------------------
1. Jay, Philip, undated, box 64, folder 70, coll. 2009097 Bimu C475 2, News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Faculty and Staff Files, Bentley Historical Library
2. Ibid.
The Philip Jay collection consists of a single series, Correspondence. The correspondence is organized into three chronological subseries, 1925-1941 (3.1 linear feet), 1942 (0.9 linear feet), and 1945-1970 (1.0 linear feet). Each of the correspondence subseries are alphabetically arranged. The correspondence is with other dental professionals and national dental organizations and also contains School of Dentistry course materials, information on fluoridation, and dental caries research materials. The fluoridation materials document the controversy surrounding fluoridation of the Michigan water supply and also include copies of Jay's remarks before the Michigan Legislature, news clippings, and assorted publications. Dental caries research materials include diet plans and grant applications.
Subjects:
Dentists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dentistry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; Water--Fluoridation.
- Correspondence, 1925-1970
  - 1925-1941
    - A (Box 1)
    - American College of Dentist's (Box 1)
    - American Dental Association (Box 1)
    - American Dental Hygienist's Association (Box 1)
    - Andersen, E. J. (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Carl A. (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Dr. G. E. (Box 1)
    - Appleton, J. L. T. (Box 1)
    - Arnold, Francis A. (Box 1)
    - Ausum, C. D. (Box 1)
    - B, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Bailey, W. E. (Box 1)
    - Baker, E. D. (Box 1)
    - Baker, F. F. (Box 1)
    - Bame, Harry (Box 1)
    - Barkley, J. A. (Box 1)
    - Barton, Dr. Paul M. (Box 1)
    - Bassett, Dr. H. (Box 1)
    - Bayne-Jones, S. (Box 1)
    - Bear, Harry (Box 1)
    - Becks, Hermann (Box 1)
    - Bellinger, Dr. Don H. (Box 1)
    - Bernstein, Dr. Peter M. (Box 1)
    - Beust, Theo B. (Box 1)
    - Bibby, Basil G. (Box 1)
    - Blaney, J. R. (Box 1)
    - Bodecker, Dr. Charles F. (Box 1)
    - Bodine, T. A. (Box 1)
    - Brake, Dr. A. J. (Box 1)
    - Brown, Stanley C. (Box 1)
    - Bumstead, C. A. (Box 1)
    - Bunting, Russell W. (Box 1)
    - Byerly, Paul R. (Box 1)
    - C, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
    - California Dental Society, Southern (Box 1)
    - Canada Dental Convention, Western (Box 1)
    - Chautauqua (Box 1)
    - Chicago Dental Society (Box 1)
    - Clifford, Dr. Eugene M. (Box 1)
    - Coleman, R. E. (Box 1)
    - Colquitt, Walter T. (Box 1)
    - Cooper, Dr. Herbert K. (Box 1)
    - Cornhusker Dental Study Club (Box 1)
    - Coyle, Dr. Raymond R. (Box 1)
    - Crebs, Dr. W. W. (Box 1)
    - D (Box 1)
    - Davis, Dr. William R. (Box 1)
    - Dean, Dr. H. T., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - DeArment, Dr. D. C. (Box 1)
    - Dental Caries Hospital Refers (Box 1)
    - Dental Cosmos (Box 1)
    - Dental Items of Interest Publishing Company, Inc. (Box 1)
    - "Diet and Dental Caries" Requests (Box 1)
    - Dietrich, Dr. C. P. (Box 1)
    - Difco Laboratories (Box 1)
    - Donovan, Dr. J. Arnold (Box 1)
    - Drake, Dr. M. L. (Box 1)
    - Dunklin, Dr. V. L. (Box 1)
    - E (Box 1)
    - Easlick, Dr. K. A. (Box 1)
    - Elliott, Dr. S. L. (Box 1)
    - Emeis, Dr. Harry Prescott (Box 1)
    - Epstein, Dr. S. B. (Box 1)
    - Espie, Dr. Kenneth C. (Box 1)
    - F (Box 1)
    - Falkenbury (Box 1)
    - Farnsworth, Dr. F. M. (Box 1)
    - Fawcett, J. C. (Box 1)
    - Fellowships-Rochester (Box 1)
    - Fineman, Joseph (Box 1)
    - Fisch, Dr. G. M. (Box 1)
    - Flatley, Dr. E. G. (Box 1)
    - Fleisch, Dr. Louis M. (Box 1)
    - Flett, Dr. Fred (Box 1)
    - Forster, Dr. B. T. (Box 1)
    - Fox, Dr. Lewis (Box 1)
    - Foy, Dr. S. A. (Box 1)
    - Fraternity (Box 1)
    - Fresch, Dr. C. A. (Box 1)
    - Freeland, Dr. W. C. (Box 1)
    - G (Box 2)
    - Gardey, Dr. Arnold (Box 2)
    - George, Dr. Robert K. (Box 2)
    - Geller, S. J. (Box 2)
    - Gerendasy, Dr. S. S. (Box 2)
    - Gies, Dr. William J. (Box 2)
    - Gilson, Dr. Thomas D. (Box 2)
    - Goodsell, Dr. J. O. (Box 2)
    - Gordon, Dr. Samuel M. (Box 2)
    - Graves, Dr. O. N. (Box 2)
    - Greater New York Dental Meeting (Box 2)
    - Green, Dr. Henry (Box 2)
    - Grenney, Dr. H. J. (Box 2)
    - Gurley, Dr. John E. (Box 2)
    - H, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Hadley, Dr. Faith P. (Box 2)
    - Hadley, Dr. G. S. (Box 2)
    - Hamilton Manufacturing Co. (Box 2)
    - Hanke, Dr. Erwin (Box 2)
    - Hatton, Dr. E. H. (Box 2)
    - Heidenreich, Dr. L. J. (Box 2)
    - Heidenreich, Dr. W. W. (Box 2)
    - Henes, Dr. R. A. (Box 2)
    - Hert, Dr. Benedict S. (Box 2)
    - Hill, Dr. L. E. (Box 2)
    - Hill, Dr. Thomas J. (Box 2)
    - Hitzeman, Mr. William F. (Box 2)
    - Hoag, Dr. E. E. (Box 2)
    - Hodes, Dr. Philip B. (Box 2)
    - Hoeffer, Dr. F. H. (Box 2)
    - Hoffman, Dr. O. E., Department of Health, Des Moines, Iowa (Box 2)
    - Hoffman, Dr. W. R., Islip, Long Island, N.Y.C. (Box 2)
    - Hollister, Dr. J. F. (Box 2)
    - Howard, Dr. H. H. (Box 2)
    - Howland, Wells (Box 2)
    - Huber, Dr. R. E. (Box 2)
    - Hughes, Dr. Harry J. (Box 2)
    - Hunt, Dr. T. H. (Box 2)
    - I (Box 2)
    - Indiana State Dental Association (Box 2)
    - J (Box 2)
    - Jirka, Frank J. (Box 2)
    - Johnson, E. Shurley (Box 2)
    - Johnston, John F. (Box 2)
    - K (Box 2)
    - Kentucky Dental Society (Box 2)
    - Kirsch, Dr. Sidonie H. (Box 2)
    - Kitchen, Dr. Paul C. (Box 2)
    - Klarmann, Dr. E. G. (Box 2)
    - Klinesteker, Dr. W. B. (Box 2)
    - Kohn, Leonard (Box 2)
    - Krasnow, Dr. Frances (Box 2)
    - Kunin, Dr. I. J. (Box 2)
    - L (Box 2)
    - Leggett, Dr. W. C. (Box 2)
    - Lehner, Dr. H. B. (Box 2)
    - Leiberman, Miss Esther (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Dr. S. J. (Box 2)
    - Liddell, Dr. George (Box 2)
    - Loubser, Dr. Dirk (Box 2)
    - Lovell, Dr. F. R. (Box 2)
    - Ludwick, Dr. Ralph W. (Box 2)
    - Mc (Box 2)
    - McBride, Dr. W. C. (Box 2)
    - McCracken, Dr. W. H. (Box 2)
    - Mac Ewan, Dr. D. C. (Box 2)
    - MacLean, Jan (Box 2)
    - MacInnes, W. R. (Box 2)
    - McLaughlin, Dr. Neil (Box 2)
    - M, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Madden, Dr. Clare K. (Box 2)
    - Mason, Dr. W. J. B. (Box 2)
    - Messner, Dr. C. T. (Box 2)
    - Miller, Dr. Fred (Box 2)
    - Minonk, Illinois (Box 2)
    - Mohn, Dr. E. J. (Box 2)
    - Murphy, Dr. Phelps J. (Box 2)
    - N (Box 3)
    - Neurohr, Dr. F. G. (Box 3)
    - Novatney, Dr. J. F. (Box 3)
    - Noyes, Dr. Harold J. (Box 3)
    - O (Box 3)
    - Oles, Dr. F. W. (Box 3)
    - Ostrander, Dr. D. G. (Box 3)
    - P, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pacific Coast Dental Conference (Box 3)
    - Patterson, O. L. (Box 3)
    - Peabody, Dr. E. C. (Box 3)
    - Peck, Dr. Milan H. (Box 3)
    - Pederson, Dr. M. C. (Box 3)
    - Pelton, Dr. W. J. (Box 3)
    - Peters, Dr. Robert (Box 3)
    - Peterson, Dr. V. E. (Box 3)
    - Pi Lambda Phi (Box 3)
    - Pinney, Dr. Benton S. (Box 3)
    - Pittsburgh Dental School (Box 3)
    - Powers, Dr. R. P. (Box 3)
    - Prada, Dr. J. W. (Box 3)
    - Prag, Dr. J. J. (Box 3)
    - Primer, Dr. B. M. (Box 3)
    - Q (Box 3)
    - R, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Raven, Clara (Box 3)
    - Reddish, G. F. (Box 3)
    - Reprint Requests (Box 3)
    - Rice, Dr. J. B. (Box 3)
    - Rogers, Dr. J. L. (Box 3)
    - Rosebury, Dr. Theodore (Box 3)
    - Rubenstein, Dr. Benjamin (Box 3)
    - Ryan, Dr. Kenneth J. (Box 3)
    - Rodriguez, F. E. (Box 3)
    - S, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Saunders, Dr. Charles, Jr. (Box 3)
    - Schaffer, Jacob (Box 3)
    - Schindler, N. M. (Box 3)
    - Schultz, Dr. L. C. (Box 3)
    - Schwartz, Dr. L. L. (Box 3)
    - Selinger, Dr. J. (Box 3)
    - Seyler, Dr. A. E. (Box 3)
    - Shaffer, Dr. Ward L. (Box 3)
    - Sherr, Dr. Max (Box 3)
    - Sherwood, Dr. C. C. (Box 3)
    - Sidenberg, Dr. B. R. (Box 3)
    - Sloane, Dr. David L. (Box 3)
    - Smith, C. M. (Box 3)
    - Smith, Dr. E. P. (Box 3)
    - Sognnals, R. F. (Box 3)
    - Sparks, Dr. A. L. (Box 3)
    - Stevens, Dr. Burr E. (Box 3)
    - Stinaff, Dr. R. K. (Box 3)
    - Striffler, Dr. H. C. (Box 3)
    - Strong, Dr. Norman H. (Box 3)
    - Stulberg, Dr. Samuel (Box 3)
    - Sturman, Dr. John (Box 3)
    - Suit, Dr. S. R. (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - True, Harry A. (Box 3)
    - U (Box 3)
    - V (Box 3)
    - Vanden Bosch, Dr. J. A. (Box 3)
    - Van Haitsma, Dr. Titus (Box 3)
    - Van Kirk, Dr. L. E. (Box 3)
    - Veeder, Dr. Borden S. (Box 3)
    - W, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Walkinshaw, Lawrence H. (Box 3)
    - Wallace & Tiernan (Box 3)
    - Walton, Dr. Charles B. (Box 3)
    - Wareham, Dr. F. L. (Box 3)
    - Washington University, 75th Anniversary Celebration (Box 3)
    - Waugh, Dr. L. M. (Box 3)
    - Wheeler, Dr. Don C. (Box 3)
    - Whipple, Dean G. H. (Box 3)
    - White, Dr. John R. (Box 3)
    - Wilkes, Dr. R. H. (Box 3)
    - Wilson, Dr. W. H. (Box 3)
    - XYZ (Box 3)
    - Yates, Stanley J. (Box 3)
    - Yeager, Dr. A. M. (Box 3)
    - Ziegler, Dr. J. E. (Box 3)
    - Ziskin, Dr. D. E. (Box 3)
    - Zoller, Walter G., Memorial Dental Clinic (Box 3)
  - 1942
    - A (Box 4)
    - Armstrong, H. M. (Box 4)
    - Arnold, Francis A., Jr. (Box 4)
    - B (Box 4)
    - C (Box 4)
    - Carter, Dr. C. W. (Box 4)
    - Clifford, Dr. F. O. (Box 4)
    - Conat, C. M. (Box 4)
    - Cowan, Dr. M. M. (Box 4)
    - D (Box 4)
    - Davis, Dr. T. S. (Box 4)
    - E (Box 4)
    - F (Box 4)
    - Finlay, Dr. E. V. (Box 4)
    - Fowle, Dr. L. C. (Box 4)
    - Fox, Dr. E. H. (Box 4)
    - Friedman, Dr. Harry M. (Box 4)
    - G (Box 4)
    - Gottlieb, B. (Box 4)
    - Grant, W. F. D. (Box 4)
    - H (Box 4)
    - Hammond, Dr. F. C. (Box 4)
    - Hospital Refer, Dental Caries (Box 4)
    - I (Box 4)
    - J (Box 4)
    - K (Box 4)
    - L (Box 4)
    - Mc (Box 4)
    - McConnell, H. W. (Box 4)
    - M (Box 4)
    - Maryland State Dental Society (Box 4)
    - Moore, Dr. G. R. (Box 4)
    - N (Box 4)
    - P (Box 4)
    - O (Box 4)
    - Q (Box 4)
    - R (Box 4)
    - Rickert, Dr. H. E. (Box 4)
    - Ross, Victor F. (Box 4)
    - S (Box 4)
    - Smith, Dr. Junius C. (Box 4)
    - T--Z, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1945-1970
    - Diet (Food Selection for a High Polyunsaturated Fatty Acid Diet), November 15, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Diet Program, 1958-1969 (Box 5)
    - Dietetics, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Dominican Diet Study (Adrian Study), 1963-1965
      - Diet Study, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
      - Food and Equipment for Adrian Study, 1964 (Box 5)
      - Recipes for Adrian Study (Box 5)
      - Study #2, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Escanaba Extension Service, 1956-1962 (Box 5)
    - Fluoridation, 1945-1967
      - Flint Dental Society, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
      - Fluoride, 1962-1969 (Box 5)
      - Fluoride Phosphate Letters, 1964 (Box 5)
      - Fluoride, Topical Application of, 1967 (Box 5)
      - Fluoridation, 1945-1955 (Box 5)
      - Fluoridation Equipment, 1965 (Box 5)
      - Fluoridation Letters, 1958-1966 (Box 5)
      - Fluoritab Corporation, 1961-1966 (Box 5)
      - Fluoridation, State of Michigan, 1967 (Box 5)
      - Highland Park Fluoridation Trial, 1958-1961 (Box 5)
      - Lansing Fluoridation, 1965 (Box 5)
      - Legislative Hearing on Fluoridation, 1963 (Box 5)
      - Lizaire, A. L., Department of Public Health, Saskatchewan, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
      - Loyola University, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
      - WJBK TV Station, 1966 (Box 5)
      - WJR Radio Station, 1960-1962 (Box 5)
      - WXYZ Radio Station, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Ireland, 1964-1970 (Box 5)
    - Jp-Jz, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Ludwick, Capt. William E., 1967 (Box 5)
    - Ma-Mg, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Mann, Dean W. R., 1967 (Box 5)
    - McConnell, Bernie E., 1961 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Department of Health, 1958-1970 (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Dental Association, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Legislature, 1966 (Box 5)
    - National Institute of Dental Research, 1959-1967 (Box 5)
    - National Institute of Health, 1958-1965 (Box 5)
    - North Carolina, University of, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Nutrition, 1965-1969
      - Conference on Teaching Nutrition in Dental Schools, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
      - Course Materials, 1965 (Box 5)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 5)
    - Parsons, Patricia A., 1966 (Box 5)
    - Ph-Po, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Pp-Pz, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Public Health, School of, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Research Methodology Course, Fall 1964 (Box 5)
    - Rhode Island, University of, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Rp-Rz, 1965 (Box 5)
    - S., 1962-1967 (Box 5)
    - Sandell, Perry, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - San Salvador Meeting, May 1963 (Box 5)
    - Sodium Fluoride, 1959-1962 (Box 5)
    - Stannous Fluoride, 1960-1965 (Box 5)
    - Stare, Frederick J., 1955-1966 (Box 5)
    - Study Section Symposium, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Szwejda, Louis F., 1960-1963 (Box 5)
    - Travis, William, 1960-1965 (Box 5)
    - Rauch-Barraco, M. J., 1966-1969 (Box 5)
    - Toothbrushing, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Toothpastes, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Upjohn Company, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - Wertheimer, Fred, Michigan Department of Health, 1947-1963 (Box 5)